片名：记忆碎片
我在哪里？某间旅馆房内
So where are you? You're in some motel room.
一觉醒来  发觉自己在旅馆房内
You just wake up, and you're in a motel room.
钥匙在这里  似乎刚刚住进来
There's the key. It feels like maybe it'sjust the first time you've been there...
但…又似乎住了一个星期
but... perhaps you've been there for a week...
甚至三个月
three months.
很难说  我不知道
It's kind of hard to say. I don't know.
只是间普通的房间
It's just an anonymous room.
这个人…
This guy.
他已经来了
He's here already.
莱尼
Lenny!
是莱纳
It's Leonard...
我告诉过你
like I told you before.
是吗？我一定是忘了
Did you? I must have forgot.
我大概提到过我的病
I guess I've already told you about my condition.
每次见面都提
Only every time I see you.
- 我的车   - 这是你的车
- My car.      - This is your car.
想耍我
You're in a playful mood.
你不应该捉弄有缺陷的人
It's not good to make fun of someone's handicap.
只是开开玩笑
Just trying to have a little fun.
绞起玻璃窗
Roll up your window.
- 是破的   - 我可以修理
- It's broken.      - I can get that fixed foryou.
- 你想去哪？福尔摩斯先生？ - 我要去一个地方
- So where to, Sherlock?        - I got a lead on a place.
你去那里到底想搞什么名堂？
What the hell you wanna go there for?
- 你认识这地方？  - 只是间破屋子
- You know it?      - Yeah. It'sjust this fucked-up building.
- 为什么要去？ - 想不起来了
- Why do you wanna go there?      - Don't remember.
- 似乎有人   - 车已经停了好几年了
- Looks like somebody's home.      - That thing's been here for years.
路上的痕迹是新的
What are you talking about? These tracks are only a few days old.
你懂得认痕迹？
Tracks? What are you? Pocahontas?
来吧
Come on!
进去看看
Let's take a look inside.
泰迪
"Teddy."
不要受他骗  是他  杀了他
"Don't believe his lies. He is the one. Kill him."
我终于找到他了  我找了多久？
I finally found him. How long have I been looking?
找到什么了吗？
Find anything?
大概没有
Didn't think so.
我们走吧
Let's go.
算了
Fuck this.
杀人偿命
You're gonna pay for what you did.
- 一命还一命   - 莱纳
- Beg forgiveness, and then you pay.      - Leonard.
神经病  你搞错了
You don't have a clue, you freak.
先向我太太认错  然后受死
Beg my wife's forgiveness before I blow your brains out.
莱纳  你真是糊里糊涂的
Leonard, you don't know what's going on.
- 知道我叫什么吗？ - 泰迪
- You don't even know my name.      - Teddy.
你靠照片才知道
That's 'cause you read it off a fucking picture.
你不知道自已是谁
You don't know who you are.
我叫莱纳•谢尔比  旧金山人
I'm Leonard Shelby. I'm from San Francisco.
那是以前的你  不是现在的你
That's who you were. That's not what you've become.
- 住口    - 你想知道吗？
- Shut your mouth.      - You want to know, Lenny?
来
Come on.
我们到地下室去
Come on. Let's go down to the basement.
我们一起下去
Let's go down, you and me, together.
你会知道自己真正是谁
Then you'll know who you really are.
不
No!
只是间普通的房子
It'sjust an anonymous room.
抽屉空空如也  只管打开看看
There's nothing in the drawers. But you look anyway.
只有本基甸社送的圣经  我当然诚心阅读了
Nothing except the Gideon Bible, which I, of course, read religiously.
你知道自己是谁  对自己的身份有点印象
You know who you are, and you know kind of all about yourself.
至于过日常生活  字条十分有用
Butjust for day-to-day stuff, notes are really useful.
萨米•杰克斯也靠字条
Sammy Jankis had the same problem...
不过他缺乏条理
but he really had no system.
他拼命写字条
He wrote himself a ridiculous amount of notes...
却乱放一通
but he'd get them all mixed up.
要有效果  就要有条理
You really do need a system if you're gonna make it work.
"不要受他的骗"
"他是凶手  杀了他"
- 嘿    - 嘿
- Hi.      - Hi.
- 我是304号房的住客  - 有什么可以效劳的  莱纳？
- I'm Mr. Shelby from 304.      - What can I do for you, Leonard?
我叫波特
Burt.
波特  我可能说过  我不接电话
Burt. I'm not sure. I think I may have asked you to hold my calls.
- 你不记得？ - 我不习惯讲电话
- You don't know?      - I think I may have. I'm not good on the phone.
对  你喜欢面谈
Right. You said you like to look people in the eye when you talk to them.
对
Yeah.
你不记得说过？
You don't remember saying that?
- 我有种病   - 病？
- That's the thing. I have this condition.      - A condition?
- 我的记忆   - 失忆？
- It's my memory.      - Amnesia?
不是  我没有短期记忆
No, no. It's different from that. I have no short-term memory.
我知道自己是谁  不过…
I know who I am. I know all about myself.
自从受了伤  我没有新记忆  什么都记不住
Since my injury, I can't make new memories. Everything fades.
我会忘记为什么跟你谈
If we talk for too long, I'll forget how we started.
我会忘记跟你谈过
Next time I see you, I'm not gonna remember this conversation.
我甚至记不得见过你
I don't even know if I've met you before.
假如我行动古怪  无礼…
So, if I seem a little strange or rude or something...
我都说过  是不是？
I've told you this before, haven't I?
是  确实太奇怪了
Yeah. I don't mean to mess with you, but it's so weird.
- 你完全记不得我？ - 记不得
- You don't remember me at all?      - No.
- 可是我们经常交谈    - 可以肯定
- We've talked a bunch of times.      - I'm sure we have.
你最后记得的是什么？
What's the last thing you remember?
我太太
My wife.
是怎样的？
What's it like?
像是刚刚醒来
It's like waking. It's like you just woke up.
一定很不爽
That must suck.
全部都调转过来
It's all backwards.
你或许知道要做什么  可是记不得做过什么
Maybe you get an idea what you want to do next, but you don't remember what you just did.
- 我却刚刚相反   - 我在这里住了多久？
- I'm exactly the opposite...      - How long have I been staying here?
- 几天   - 而你替我阻挡来电？
- Couple of days.      - And you're holding my calls?
- 就像你吩咐的   - 除了这个人
- Like you said.      - Okay, but this guy's an exception.
- 认识他吗？ - 他是你的朋友
- You know this guy?      - Yeah, it's your friend, right?
你怎么知道？
What makes you think he's my friend?
- 我见过你们在一起   - 他不是我的朋友
- I just saw you together, that's all.      - He's not my friend.
- 那好吧   - 假如他打电话来…
- Okay.      - If he calls or if he shows up here...
或者亲自来  通知我
give me a call in my room, okay?
他叫泰迪？
His name's Teddy?
- 泰迪  对了   - 好的
- Teddy, yeah.      - All right.
我希望没有给你添麻烦
Look, I hope my condition's not gonna be a problem for you.
只要你记得结账就行
No, not as long as you remember to pay the bill.
好的
Yeah. Okay.
- 40块    - 40块
- Forty.      - Forty.
那个人…
This guy...
已经来了
He's here already.
莱尼
Lenny!
"剃"
要有效  就要有条理
You really need a system if you're gonna make it work.
要相信自己的笔迹
You kind of learn to trust your own handwriting.
那是日常生活的重要部分  你为自己写备忘字条
That becomes an important part of your life. You write yourself notes.
放字条的地方...也很重要
Where you put your notes... That also becomes important.
外衣要有六个口袋
You need a jacket that's got like six pockets in it.
各个口袋有各自的功能
Particular pockets for particular things.
要养成井井有条的习惯
You just kind of learn to know where things go and how the system works.
要防范别人故意混淆你
And you have to be wary of other people writing stuff for you that is not gonna make sense...
替你乱写字条
or is gonna lead you astray.
世上总有那种人
I don't know. I guess people try and take advantage of somebody with this condition.
如果你把把关键的资料…
If you have a piece of information which is vital...
纹在身上  是个能行得通的办法
writing on your body instead of on a piece of paper can be the answer.
可以永久备忘
It's just a permanent way of keeping a note.
哪位？
Who is this?
"记住萨米•杰克斯"
"Remember Sammy Jankis."
"事实…"
先生  你忘记拿走这个了
Excuse me, sir. You left these at your table.
谢谢
Thanks.
林肯街怎么走？
Lincoln Street?
沿第六街一直向东走
Go straight out on Sixth Street. Go east all the way...
- 等一下  我要写下来   - 很容易  只是直走
- Hold on. I'm gonna write this down.      - It's easy. Just go straight...
我的确需要写下来
Trust me. I need to write this down.
"特惠旅馆"
"The Discount Inn."
特惠旅馆
Discount Inn.
娜塔莉娅
Natalie.
我的车
My car.
泰迪
Teddy.
"莱纳收"   "娜塔莉娅寄"
约翰•爱德华•盖玛
"John Edward Gammell."
他自称泰迪
This guy told me his name was Teddy.
"不要受他骗"
"Don't believe his lies."
- 喂？ - 盖玛先生？
- Yeah?      - Mr. Gammell?
- 莱尼  是你吗？ - 你是约翰•盖玛？
- Lenny, is that you?      - John Gammell?
是泰迪啊  不要走开  我马上来
Lenny, it's Teddy. Stay there. I'll be right over.
好的  我等你
Okay. I'll be waiting.
"照片  房子  车  朋友 敌人"
"提防自己的弱点"
"相信事实"
"记忆误人"
"事实1：男人"    "事实2：白种"
白种男人
"White. Male."
名叫约翰…
"First name: John."
姓盖玛…
"Last name: G" for Gammell.
"事实5：毒贩"    "事实6：车牌 SG1371U"
毒贩  车牌
"Drugs. License plate."
"SG13...
7IU."
"车牌 SG1371U"
是他
It's him.
"泰迪"
终于找到了你这个贱人
I found you, you fuck.
"不要受他骗  是他"
"约翰•G奸杀我妻子"
"杀了他"
我记不得跟你谈过
You said we talked before. I don't remember that.
不是失忆症  我只是记不得受伤以后的事
Yeah, but it's not amnesia. I remember everything up until my injury.
我没有新记忆  所以我不记得和你谈过
I just can't make new memories. So I can't remember talking to you.
我们谈了萨米•杰克斯？
What did we talk about? Oh, Sammy Jankis.
因为萨米•杰克斯和我…
I guess I tell people about Sammy to help them understand.
都有短期失忆
Sammy's story helps me understand my own situation.
萨米为自己写备忘字条  不过他乱放字条
Sammy wrote himself endless amounts of notes, but he got mixed up.
我的方法更有效
I have a more graceful solution to the memory problem.
我有条不紊
I'm disciplined and organized.
所以能够应付日常生活
I use habit and routine to make my life possible.
萨米没有推动力去帮自己记忆
Sammy had no drive, no reason to make it work.
我呢？我有推动力
Me? Yeah, I got a reason.
"今午一点见娜塔莉娅取消息"
"Today, 1:00 p.m. Meet Natalie for info."
"她也失去爱人"
"She has also lost someone."
"会同情你  帮你"
"She will help you out of pity."
- 你是娜塔莉娅？ - 你不记得我
- Natalie?      - You don't remember me.
- 对不起  我应该解释  我有…   - 你解释过  莱尼
- Sorry. I should have explained. I have this...      - You did explain, Lenny.
请叫我莱纳  我太太叫我莱尼
Please call me Leonard. My wife called me Lenny.
- 我知道  你说过   - 可能也说过讨厌被人叫莱尼
- Yeah, I know. You told me.      - Then I probably told you how much I hated it.
是的
Yeah.
可以取下墨镜吗？
Do you mind taking your glasses off? It's hard for me to...
谢谢  你有消息给我？
Thanks. So you have information for me?
- 你的字条那样写？ - 对
- Is that what your little note says?      - Yeah.
单靠字条生活  一定很辛苦
Must be tough living your life according to a couple of scraps of paper.
洗衣单和杂货单调乱
You mix your laundry list with your grocery list...
那就麻烦了
and you'll end up eating your underwear for breakfast.
所以你甚至把备忘纹在身上
I guess that's why you have those freaky tattoos.
日子确实不好过
Yeah, it's tough. It's almost impossible.
记不得你  对不起  不要见怪
I'm sorry I don't rememberyou. It's nothing personal.
我的确有消息给你
I do have information for you.
你给我个车牌
You gave me a license plate number.
我去交通部查过
Had my friend at DMV trace it.
猜猜是谁的
Guess what name came up.
约翰•爱德华•盖玛   约翰•G
John Edward Gammell. John G.
- 你认识他？ - 不
- Do you know him?      - No.
不过照片上的人看起来很熟悉
But his face on his driver's license looked really familiar.
他可能来过酒吧
I think he's been in the bar, maybe.
这是他的车牌和照片副本
Here's a copy of his license, his registration, photo and all.
你真的要这样做？
Are you sure you want this?
- 我有没有说过他做过什么？ - 有
- Have I told you what this man did?      - Yeah.
那你就不用问了
Then you shouldn't have to ask.
不过  你即使报了仇...
But even if you get revenge, you're not gonna remember it.
你也不会记得
You're not even gonna know that it happened.
妻子的仇不可不报  记不记得无所谓
My wife deserves vengeance. Doesn't make any difference whether I know about it.
即使记不得  依然值得做
Just because there are things I don't remember doesn't make my actions meaningless.
即使闭上眼睛  世界并没有消失
The world doesn't just disappear when you close your eyes, does it?
我可以拍张照片来提醒自已
Anyway, maybe I'll take a photograph to remind myself...
或者再纹个备忘录在身上
get another freaky tattoo.
再说说她的事吧
Tell me about her again.
为什么？
Why?
因为你喜欢记起她
Because you like to remember her.
她漂亮
She was beautiful.
- 对我来说  她是完美的  - 不要顺口说
- To me, she was perfect.      - No. Don't just recite the words.
闭上眼睛去回忆她
Close your eyes... and remember her.
我可以感受到细节
You can just feel the details.
一些平时懒得回忆的细节
The bits and pieces you never bothered to put into words.
那些非常时刻…
And you can feel these extreme moments...
重现眼前
even if you don't want to.
印象愈发清晰
You put these together, and you get the feel of a person.
我更加怀念她
Enough to know how much you miss them...
也更加痛恨凶手
and how much you hate the person who took them away.
我写了个地址在上面
I added an address in here.
也许有用  是近郊的一间荒屋
It might be useful. It's an abandoned place outside of town.
我的朋友曾经在那里贩毒
A guy I knew used to do bigger deals there.
四周没有人
It's isolated.
好极了
Sounds perfect.
- 我应不应该付你…  - 不用  我不是为钱
- Do I owe you any...      - I wasn't helping you for money.
- 对不起  - 没关系
- I'm sorry.      - It's okay.
我知道你有病
See, you have this condition.
还住在优惠旅馆？你落在我家里的
Are you still staying at the Discount Inn, room 304? You left it at my place.
嗯
Yeah.
- 旅馆招待好吗？ - 我记不得了
- They treating you okay?      - I don't remember.
你和我有个共同点
You know what we have in common?
我们都懂得生存
We are both survivors.
保重  莱纳
You take care, Leonard.
"记住萨米•杰克斯"
"Remember Sammy Jankis."
我本来在保险公司工作
I met Sammy through work. Insurance. I was an investigator.
负责调查保险索赔
I'd investigate the claims to see which ones were phony.
专长是辨别真与假
I had to see through people's bullshit.
这专长现在派上了大用场
It was useful experience, 'cause now it's my life.
现在我靠观察去辨认…
When I meet someone, I don't know if I've met them before.
眼前的人是不是相识的
I have to look in their eyes and try and figure them out.
我知道观言辨色…
My job taught me the best way to find out what someone knew was just let them talk...
是了解人的最好办法
and watch the eyes and the body language.
譬如  一个人一边谈话一边擦鼻子…
If someone scratches their nose while they're talking, experts tell you it means they're lying.
那个人可能在说谎或者紧张  紧张的原因很多
It really means they're nervous. People get nervous for all sorts of reasons.
视乎情形而定
It's all about context.
对  我是观人高手
Yeah, I was good.
第一个观察的人是萨米
Sammy was my first real challenge.
莱尼  还以为你离开了本地
Yo, Lenny! I thought you split for good.
- 情况有变    - 看得出来
- Things change.         - So I see.
- 我叫泰迪  - 我大概提到过我的病
- My name's Teddy.      - I guess I've told you about my condition.
每次见面都提  来  我请你吃午餐
Only every time I see you. Come on, I'll buy you lunch.
- 我有没有提过萨米•杰克斯？ - 有
- Have I told you about Sammy Jankis?      - Yeah.
我听得好厌  约翰•G呢？你认为他还在？
I'm sick of hearing about the guy. What about John G? You think he's still here?
- 谁？ - 约翰•G  你要找的人
- Who?      - Johnny G, the guy you're looking for.
- 你为了找他  才留在本地？ - 也许吧
- That's why you haven't left town, am I right?      - Maybe.
- 莱纳  你非小心不可   - 为什么？
- Leonard, look. You have to be very careful.      - Why?
你提过有人想误导你…
The other day you mentioned that maybe somebody was trying to set you up...
让你杀错人
get you to kill the wrong guy.
我会凭事实去判断
I go on facts, not recommendations, but thank you.
怎能凭字条、照片去决定杀谁？
Lenny, you can't trust a man's life to your little notes and pictures.
- 为什么不能？ - 因为字条未必可靠
- Why not?      - Because your notes could be unreliable.
- 记忆也未必可靠    - 拜托
- Memory's unreliable.      - Oh, please!
记忆不准确  甚至不合用
No, really. Memory's not perfect. It's not even that good.
问问警察吧  目击证供未必可靠
Ask the police. Eyewitness testimony is unreliable.
警察不是凭记忆缉凶
The cops don't catch a killer by sitting around remembering stuff.
警察搜集事实  做笔记  然后作出结论
They collect facts, they make notes, and they draw conclusions.
凭事实  不是凭记忆
Facts, not memories.
我以前是调查员  所以知道
That's how you investigate. I know. It's what I used to do.
形状、颜色等细节  未必记得准
Memory can change the shape of a room. It can change the color of a car.
可以记错
And memories can be distorted.
记忆只是一种演绎  不是纪录
They're just an interpretation. They're not a record.
掌握事实  就不用靠记忆
They're irrelevant if you have the facts.
你非报仇不可？
You really want to get this guy, don't you?
他杀死我的妻子  夺去我的记忆
He killed my wife. He took away my fucking memory.
毁灭我生存的能力
He destroyed my ability to live.
你还活着
You're living.
完全为了报仇
Only for revenge.
那么我们把这坏蛋找出来  你住在哪里？
Then we'll get the bastard. Where you staying?
特惠旅馆
The Discount Inn.
我不知道是哪间房  我没有钥匙
I don't know what room. I haven't got my key.
可能落在了房里
Probably left it in your room.
我是房客  不见了钥匙
Hi. I'm checked in here, but I think I've misplaced my key.
你好  莱纳  可能在房里
How you doing, Leonard? Probably in the room, right?
- 我的钥匙呢？ - 糟糕
- Don't see my key anywhere.      - Shit.
进错房间了  你现在住304号房
This is the wrong room. You're in 304 now.
- 对不起  我搞错了  - 这不是我的房间？
- I'm sorry. I fucked up.      - This is not my room?
不是  我们走吧
No. Let's go.
为什么有我的笔迹？
Why is this my handwriting?
以前是  现在你住304
This was your room, but now you're in 304.
- 我什么时候住过这间？ - 上个星期
- When was I in here?      - Last week.
不过我再多租你一间
But then I rented you another room on top of it.
- 为什么？ - 生意冷淡
- Why?      - Business is slow.
…你既然有这种病…
I told my boss about your condition and stuff...
我们于是多租一间给你
and he said, "Try and rent him another room."
我究竟租了几间？
How many rooms am I checked into in this shit-hole?
只是两间  到目前为止
Just two, so far.
起码你坦白承认占我便宜
At least you're being honest about ripping me off.
你反正不会记得
You're not gonna remember anyway.
用不着那样坦白
You don't have to be that honest, Burt.
莱纳  每次都应该取收条
Leonard, always get a receipt.
我会记下来
Yeah. I'm gonna write that down.
"今午一点见娜塔莉娅取消息"
- 现在几点了？ - 12点45分
- What time is it?      - Quarter to 1:00.
你房间的…
Your room's...
- 娜塔莉娅    - 你记不得我
- Natalie?      - You don't remember me.
萨米•杰克斯的保险索赔十分奇特
I'd just become an investigator when I came across Sammy.
是我接手的第一宗案子
Mr. Samuel R. Jankis. Strangest case ever.
萨米58岁  半退休会计师
You know, the guy's a 58-year-old semiretired accountant.
遇到交通意外  本来不算严重
He and his wife had been in this car accident. Nothing too serious.
奇怪的是  他记不住东西
But he's acting funny. He can't get a handle on what's going on.
医生怀疑脑部受伤
The doctors find some possible damage to the hippocampus.
但无法证实萨米的记忆只有几分钟
Nothing conclusive, but Sammy can't remember anything for more than a couple of minutes.
于是什么都不能做  医药费昂贵
Can't work, can't do shit. The medical bills pile up.
他的妻子通知了保险公司  公司派我调查
His wife calls the insurance company, and I get sent in.
我初次查案  于是查得格外认真
Now, this is my first big claims investigation, so I really check into it.
萨米思考没问题  不过他没有新记忆
Sammy can think just fine, but he can't make any new memories.
只记得几分钟内的事
He could only remember things for a couple of minutes.
- 这位是莱纳先生   - 他看电视...
- This is Mr. Shelby.    - He'd watch TV...
但过目就忘
but anything longer than a couple of minutes was too confusing.
记得后面的  却忘了前面的  他喜欢看广告  因为广告简短
He couldn't remember how it began. He liked commercials. They were short.
萨米  到时间打针了
Sammy. It's time for my shot.
不可思议的是…
The crazy part was that this guy...
这个连电视也没法看的人…
who couldn't even follow the plot of Green Acres anymore...
却能够做复杂的事
could do the most complicated things...
"胰岛素"
只要意外前学会的…
as long as he learned them before the accident...
专心去做就行
and as long as he kept his mind on what he was doing.
轻点
Be gentle.
医生说有一种罕见的病叫"杆脉失忆"
The doctors assure me there's a real condition called anterograde memory loss...
也就是短期失忆
or short-term memory loss.
很罕见  但确实有
It's rare, but legit.
不过  我每次见到他…
But every time I see him...
从他的眼神察觉到…
I catch this look...
他好像有点认得我
this slight look of recognition.
他却自称一点都认不得
But he says he can't remember me at all.
萨米  不要紧  我开  我开
Sammy, it's okay. I got it. I got it.
- 你好  莱纳先生   - 你好  杰克斯太太
- Hi, Mr. Shelby.      - Hi, Mrs. Jankis.
我怀疑他在演戏
I can read people, and I'm thinking: Bad actor.
于是要求再做检验
So now I'm suspicious, and I order more tests.
醒来
Awake.
我在哪里？
Where am I?
某人的卧室
Somebody's bedroom.
一定是她的房间
It must be her room.
不过  她是谁？
But who is she?
只是我
It's only me.
- 睡得好吗？ - 好  你呢？
- Did you sleep okay?      - Yeah. You?
糟糕  我有地方要去
Oh, shit. I gotta be someplace.
- 相当怪异   - 这很有用
- It's pretty weird.      - It's useful.
你从不把电话写在手上？
You never write a phone number on your hand?
我今天要去交通部查查车牌的事
I should be able to talk to my friend today about the license plate.
- 对  车牌   - 约翰•G的车牌
- Yeah, the license plate.      - John G.'s license plate.
你把车牌纹在你的大腿上
You have it tattooed on your thigh.
娜塔莉娅
"Natalie."
她也失去爱人
"She has also lost someone.
会同情你  帮你
She will help you out of pity."
只要是本州的车牌…
If it's registered in this state...
几秒钟就能查出车主资料
it should only take a couple seconds to pull up his license and registration.
我一有资料就通知你
I'll call you as soon as I talk to him.
不如现在就约定什么时候见面吧
Do you think we could just arrange a meeting now? I'm not too good on the phone.
多谢你这样帮我…
It's great that you that you're helping me like this.
我帮你  因为你帮过我
I'm helping you because you helped me.
那么  下次见面你会记得我吗？
So next time you see me, will you remember me?
我认为你会
I think you will.
对不起
I'm sorry.
莱尼  可以把衣服还给我吗？
Lenny, before you go, could I have my shirt back, please?
莱尼  还以为你离开了本地
Yo, Lenny! I thought you split for good.
萨米不能够用一般的方法去学习
Sammy couldn't pick up any new skills at all.
不过  我认为他可以用惯性法
But I find something in my research: Conditioning.
重复又重复去学  一定能学会
Sammy should still be able to learn through repetition.
就像骑单车一样  熟能生巧
It's how you learn stuff like riding a bike. You just get better through practice.
没有短期记忆  也可以学会
It's a completely different part of the brain from the short-term memory.
我请医生检验萨米对惯性的反应
So I had the doctors test Sammy's response to conditioning.
随便拣三件东西
Just pick up any three objects.
这就算检验？
That's a test?
我考会计执照  遇上你们就好了
Where were you guys when I did my CPA?
对不起
Sorry.
搞什么？
Ow! What the fuck?
- 是检验  萨米   - 检验你个死人头
- It's a test, Sammy.      - Test this, you fucking quack.
有几样通了电
Some of the objects were electrified.
会让他稍微触电
They'd give him a small shock. They kept repeating the test...
通电的总是相同那几样
always with the same objects electrified.
目的是看看萨米能不能无须记忆…
The point was to see if Sammy could learn to avoid the electrified objects...
单凭本能去避开通电的
not by memory, but by instinct.
娜塔莉娅  是不是？这个该死的达德是谁？
Natalie, right? Who the fuck is Dodd?
达德
- 大概再不用理会他了   - 你给我惹了什么麻烦？
- Guess I don't have to worry about him anymore.      - What the fuck have you got me into?
进来吧
Come inside.
- 他是谁？ - 冷静点
- Who is he?      - Calm down. Okay?
这件事你主动帮我  跟你的调查没有关系
This is my problem. You offered to help. It has nothing to do with your investigation.
你给我惹了什么麻烦？
How did you get me into this?
你知道他打伤我  就主动帮我
You offered to help when you saw what he did to my face.
- 我怎么知道他打你？  - 因为我告诉了你
- How do I know he did that to your face?      - Because I came straight to you after he did it.
并请你帮忙
I showed you what he did, and I asked you to help me.
- 而我相信你的一面之词？ - 是
- And I just take your word?      - Yeah.
有些事情不对劲
Something doesn't feel right.
有人愚弄我  想误导我去杀错人
I think someone's fucking with me, trying to get me to kill the wrong guy.
- 你有没有？ - 有没有什么？
- Did you?      - What?
- 杀他？ - 当然没有
- Kill him?      - Of course not!
嘿
Hey.
坐下来  好吗？
Sit down, okay? Sit.
这件事跟你无关
This has nothing to do with you.
你帮我  我很感激
You helped me out, and I'm grateful.
要用火烧
You have to burn them.
莱纳  你是自愿帮我的  相信你自己吧
Leonard, you decided to help me. Trust yourself.
相信自己的判断
Trust your own judgment. You can question everything.
- 你不能什么都怀疑   - 有些事情可以肯定
- You can never know anything for sure.      - There are things you know for sure.
比如呢？
Such as?
我敲一敲会有什么声音
I know what that's gonna sound like when I knock on it.
我捡起来会有什么感觉
I know what that's gonna feel like when I pick it up.
所谓肯定…只是自以为错不了的记忆
See? Certainties. It's the kind of memory you take for granted.
我只有未受伤前的记忆
You know, I can remember so much.
主要是…关于她
The feel of the world... and her.
她已经不在人世
She's gone.
我现在只能靠写字条过日子
And the present is trivia, which I scribble down as fucking notes!
不要焦急  放松
Hey. Come on. Try and relax. Come on.
放松不容易
It's not easy for me to relax, you know?
脱掉外衣吧
Come on. Take your jacket off.
脱吧
Now. Come on.
嘿
Hey.
想不到你是那种人
Didn't think you were the type.
是反转的
It's backwards.
过来
Come here.
这里呢？
What about here?
也许等找到他的时候
Maybe it's for when I find him.
我也失去过爱人
I've lost somebody too.
一定很难过
I'm sorry.
他叫杰米
His name was Jimmy.
- 发生了什么事？ - 他去见人
- What happened to him?      - He went to meet somebody.
一去不回
He never came back.
- 见谁？ - 一个叫泰迪的人
- Who did he go to meet?      - A guy called Teddy.
警察找不到他？
What do the police think?
警察不会理会杰米那种人
They don't look too hard for guys like Jimmy.
你找到那个约翰•G…
When you find this guy, this John G...
打算怎样？
what are you gonna do?
我要杀掉他
I'm gonna kill him.
我也许可以帮你找他
Maybe I can help you find him.
我不知道她起床了多久
I don't even know how long she's been gone.
我醒来时  她已经不在
It's like I've woken up in bed and she's not here...
大概是上了洗手间吧
because she's gone to the bathroom or something.
不过  总觉得…
But somehow I just...
她不会再回到床上来
I just know she's never gonna come back to bed.
假如我能够伸手过去摸摸她那边的床...
If I could just reach over and touch her side of the bed...
就会知道是冷的
I would know that it was cold.
不过  我不能
But I can't.
我知道她不会再回来
I know I can't have her back.
我不想早上醒来  以为她还在
But I don't want to wake up in the morning thinking she's still here.
我独自躺在这里  不知道躺了多久
I lie here not knowing how long I've been alone.
我怎么能够康复？
How can I heal?
感觉不到时间…我怎么能够康复？
How am I supposed to heal if I can't... feel time?
她也失去了爱人
"She has also lost someone.
会同情你  帮你
She will help you out of pity."
他们检验了萨米几个月
They kept testing Sammy for months...
通电的总是相同的几样
always with the same objects carrying the electrical charge.
搞什么鬼？
Ow! What the fuck?
- 是检验  萨米  - 验你个死人头
- It's a test, Sammy.      - Test this, you fucking quack!
萨米即使完全短期失忆…
Even with total short-term memory loss...
应该能够靠本能避免捡错物件
Sammy should have learned to instinctively stop picking up the wrong objects.
谁都能靠惯性去学习  萨米完全不能
All the previous cases responded to conditioning. Sammy didn't respond at all.
于是证实他所患的是心理病  不是生理病
It was enough to suggest that his condition was psychological, not physical.
保险不保心理  我们拒绝赔偿
We turned down his claim on the grounds that he wasn't covered for mental illness.
医药费由杰克斯太太负担  我升职
His wife got stuck with the bills, and I got a big promotion.
惯性对萨米起不了作用
Conditioning didn't work for Sammy, so he became helpless.
对我却有效
But it works for me.
我不像萨米
I live the way Sammy couldn't.
我能够靠习惯而生活
Habit and routine make my life possible.
靠惯性  靠本能
Conditioning. Acting on instinct.
一觉醒来
Awake.
我在哪里？
Where am I?
旅馆房间里
Motel room.
某家旅馆房间里
Some anonymous motel room.
虽然抽屉空空如也  我还是要打开来看看
Nothing in the drawers, but I'll take a look anyway.
只有一本基甸社送的圣经
Nothing except the Gideon Bible.
开门
Lenny! Open up!
等一等
Just a minute.
开门
Open the door.
莱尼？
Lenny.
"泰迪" "5550134"
开门
Open the door.
快开门
Come on!
泰迪
Hi, Teddy.
你玩够了没有？
Finished playing with yourself, Lenny?
我明白了
I get it.
隔壁有人在亲热
Amorous neighbors.
你来做什么？
What are you doing here?
是你叫我来的  你说要我帮忙
You called me. You said you needed my help.
我是看在朋友的份上才帮你的
I've had more rewarding friendships than this one.
虽然总是得忍受你一遍遍地唠叨
Although I do get to keep telling the same jokes.
怎么回事？
What the fuck is that?
- 是谁？ - 你不认识？
- Who the fuck is that?      - You don't know him?
不认识  我应该认识吗？
No! Should I?
等一等
Wait a minute.
- 是不是约翰•G？ - 相信不是
- Is that John G?      - I don't think so.
- 你没有记下来？ - 我还没记就睡着了
- You don't think so? You didn't write it down?      - I might've fallen asleep before I did.
真离谱
For Christ's sakes!
问他吧
Ask him.
你叫什么？
What's your name?
你的名字
Your name.
- 达德    - 谁打伤了你？
- Dodd.      - Who did this to you?
- 什么？ - 谁打伤了你？
- What?      - Who did this to you?
你
You did.
- 我不会帮你杀人  - 不  让我想想
- I'm not gonna help you kill that guy.      - No, just let me think for a minute.
达德
"弄走他  问娜塔莉娅"
娜塔莉娅  谁是娜塔莉娅？
Okay, Natalie. Who's Natalie?
- 哪个娜塔莉娅？ - 为什么问？
- Natalie who?      - Why?
- 说不定我认识她  - 我们要把他弄走
- Maybe I know her.      - Look. We gotta get him out of here.
好的  好的
All right, all right.
他一定有车
He's gotta have a car, right?
送他上车  然后吓跑他
We take him down to his car, tell him to get the fuck out of town or we're gonna kill him.
他在流血  怎么出去？
We can't walk him out of here tied up and bleeding.
- 他怎样上来的？ - 不知道
- How the fuck did you get him up here?      - I don't know.
你不知道？
You don't know.
我知道这不是我的房间
Yes, I do. This is not my room.
一定是他的  我们自己走吧
It must be his room. Great! Let's go.
- 不可以把他留在这里  - 为什么？
- No, no. We can't just leave him here.      - Why not?
女工发现  会报警  他认得我们
Because the maid's gonna walk in. She'll see him, call the cops. He can ID us.
先替他松绑...
Okay. We untie him...
清理一下  然后用枪押走
we clean him up, and we march him out of here with a gun in his back.
枪？哪里有枪？
A gun. Why would I have a gun?
一定是他的  我这种人不会有枪
It must be his. I don't think they'd let someone like me carry a gun.
你有枪就不得了
Fucking hope not.
哪一部？
Which one?
不如偷了他的车  作为惩戒
We should probably steal his car. You know, teach him a lesson.
住口
Shut up.
你开着美州豹  当然不想偷
That's all right for you to say. You're the one with the Jag.
上车  我载他  你随后来
Get in. I'm gonna ride with him. You follow us.
把你的车钥匙拿来
Give me your keys.
你开自己的车吧
Take your own car.
- 他害怕吗？ - 他怕你那撇小胡子
- So was he scared?      - Yeah. I think it was your sinister mustache.
扯蛋  你应该偷他的车
Fuck you. You should have stolen his car.
- 这辆有什么不好？ - 你想交换吗？
- Why? What's wrong with this one?      - Nothing. You want to trade?
你打算怎么样？
So what do you do now?
我要查个清楚
I'm going to find out what the fuck that was all about.
娜塔莉娅  是不是？这个该死的达德是谁？
Natalie, right? Who the fuck is Dodd?
"达德"
萨米的妻子要负担…
Sammy's wife was crippled by the cost of supporting him...
丈夫沉重的医药费
and fighting the company's decision.
不过  她耿耿于怀的不是钱
But it wasn't the money that got to her.
我没说过萨米在假装
I never said that Sammy was faking.
萨米  我想你替我办一件事
Sammy, I have an idea.
我只说是心理病  不是生理病
Just that his problem was mental, not physical.
我要你把这支笔装到口袋里
I want you to have a pen in your pocket, okay?
- 而是不明白丈夫的病况  - 还要带着一本记事簿
- But she couldn't understand.      - You're gonna have a pad in your pocket.
- 我做错了什么？ - 你没有做错什么
- I did something wrong?      - You did something wrong!
你当然做错了  我们得想想办法
We're gonna deal with it. We're gonna try harder.
她觉得  假如自己的丈夫…
She looks into his eyes and sees the same person.
患的不是生理病  应该可以痊愈
If it's not a physical problem, he should just snap out of it.
- 爱伦打过电话来    - 爱伦打过电话来？
- Ellen called!      - Ellen called?
- 爱伦今天不能来  爱伦不来了  - 对不起
- Ellen can't come today! Ellen can't come!      - Okay. I'm sorry!
- 对不起 我已经尽力了   - 要更加努力
- I'm sorry. I'm trying. I'm sorry.      - Try harder!
我让她怀疑丈夫患心理病
So good old Leonard Shelby from the insurance company gives her the seed of doubt...
就像我让医生怀疑一样
just like he gave it to the doctors.
我从未说过他假装
But I never said that he was faking. I never said that.
我不觉得喝醉过
I don't feel drunk.
- 喂  - 糟糕！
- Hello?      - Shit.
打扫
Housekeeping.
- 现在不方便    - 对不起
- Not right now.      - I'm sorry.
好吧
Okay.
为娜塔莉娅收拾达德  叫泰迪帮忙
"Dodd. Put him onto Teddy orjust get rid of him for Natalie."
达德
Dodd.
收拾他  问娜塔莉娅
Get rid of him. Ask Natalie.
泰迪  泰迪
Teddy, Teddy.
请留下你的电话号码
Leave your number. You know what to do.
这个信息是给泰迪的
Yeah. This is a message for Teddy.
我在顶峰旅馆  6号房
I'm at the Mountcrest Inn of Fifth Street, room six.
请尽快来  很重要
I need you to come over as soon as you get this. It's important.
我是莱纳  拜拜
This is Leonard. Thanks. Bye.
妈的
Fuck.
杰克斯太太不明白  记忆是强逼不来的
What Mrs. Jankis didn't understand was that you can't bully someone into remembering.
施压只有弄巧反拙
The more pressure you're under, the harder it gets.
给我打电话  好吗？
Then call me back?
我在做什么？
Okay. What am I doing?
我在追这个人
I'm chasing this guy.
不  他在追我
No. He's chasing me.
妈的
Fuck.
达德  白种人
"Dodd. White guy.
顶峰旅馆
Mountcrest Inn on Fifth Street."
我不会放过你  贱种
I'll get the jump on you, you fucker.
顶峰旅馆
妈的
Fuck.
对不起
Sorry.
我需要武器
I need a weapon.
这件合用
This'll do.
我不觉得喝醉过
I don't feel drunk.
"事实5：毒贩"
我认识他吗？
Do I know this guy?
他好像认识我
He seems to know me.
怎么回事？
What the fuck?
- 我喜欢你的这辆车    - 谢谢
- I like your car.      - Thank you.
- 在哪里买的？ - 你有兴趣买？
- Where'd you get it?      - Are you interested in buying one?
你觉得我不起眼？
I haven't made a strong enough impression on you?
不用太自卑
I wouldn't be too hard on yourself.
我在做什么？
Okay. What am I doing?
"事实5：毒贩"
哪位？
Who is this?
哎呦
Ouch.
- 你怎么可以读完又读？ - 好看嘛
- How can you read that again?      - It's good.
你似乎读过上千次
Yeah, but you've read it, like, a thousand times.
我喜欢读
I enjoy it.
读小说  不知道下文才有趣
I always thought the pleasure of a book was in wanting to know what happens next.
不要那样扫兴
Don't be a prick.
我完全因为喜欢读而读
I'm not reading it to annoy you. I enjoy it.
让我读下去  好不好？
Just let me read, please.
可能以前烧过
Probably tried this before.
可能已经烧掉你很多遗物
Probably burned truckloads of your stuff.
总是忘不了你
Can't remember to forget you.
是
Yeah.
嗯
Uh-huh.
情况跟我所掌握的资料一致
Sir, that'd certainly be in keeping with some of my own discoveries.
我希望多了解毒品方面的事
I was hoping for a little more on the drugs angle. Can you hang on a sec?
警方报告提到凶手车里有毒品
The police report mentioned the drugs found in the car outside my house.
车是失窃的  车上遍布凶手的指纹
The car was stolen, but his prints were all over it.
我认识一位警察  报告是他给我的
I got friends in the department. They gave me a copy of it.
我做保险  有机会认识警察
I dealt with the police a lot in my insurancejob.
因为我这个病  我没法记得整份报告
With my condition, it's really tough. I can't keep it all in mind at once.
只好记要紧的  报告有几页不见了
I have to summarize the different sections. And there's pages missing.
并不完整
I guess I've been trying to log them all.
有部分被删掉了  奇怪
I don't know why these are crossed out.
不过  警方并不追缉约翰•G
But they weren't even looking for John G.
认为没有必要
The stuffthey found in the car fit in with what they believed had happened...
所以不了了之
so they didn't chase any of it up.
亲爱的
Honey.
亲爱的  很晚了
Honey, it's late.
没事吧？
Everything okay?
你没事吧？
You okay in there?
满意吗？
Was it good for you?
什么？要我锁门？
What? Was I supposed to lock the door?
不用
No.
你走吧
I'd like you to leave now.
凶手车里有毒品  是个关键
There's something about the drugs stashed in the car that doesn't ring true for me.
警方说凶手是吸毒的
Because the police claim the guy was an addict...
打劫我家  是为了有钱买毒品
needing money to score, which I think is bullshit...
他已经有大批毒品  还用打劫吗？
'cause he's not gonna go breaking into places while he's still got a stash that big.
我认为约翰•G用毒品栽赃嫁货
I think John G. Left it there or planted it there.
你怎么知道？
How do you know that?
对了  怪不得
Shit. That's true. It fits.
那么他是毒贩了
So he's a dealer.
等一等
Hang on a sec.
事实5：毒贩
现在有头绪了
Now we're getting somewhere.
特惠旅馆
"Discount Inn."
女伴服务
金发女郎  好
Yeah, okay. Blonde's fine.
对了
That's what they say.
特惠旅馆  304号房间
The Discount Inn. 304.
我叫莱纳
Leonard.
想怎么样？
What then?
我们上床  你等我睡着
We just go to bed. You wait for me to fall asleep.
然后上厕所  用力关门
You go into the bathroom and you slam the door.
- 用力关门？ -用力到吵醒我
- Slam it?      - Yeah. Loud enough to wake me up.
- 只是这样吗？ - 只是这样
- And that's it?      - That's it.
先把这些东西四处放
First I just need you to put these things around the room.
假装是你的东西 你的卧室
Just pretend they're your things and that this is your bedroom.
- 要我穿上去吗？ - 不用  就好像你刚刚脱下来
- Should I wear it?      - No. Just like you took it off or something.
我不要你用  对不起
I don't want you to use it. I'm sorry.
只要你随便放在房里
I just mean put them around the room...
就像是你的东西
as ifthey were your things.
你喜欢怎么样就怎么样好了
Whatever gets you off.
我不怪警方不理会
I can't blame the cops for not taking me seriously.
我的病不容易明白
This is a difficult condition for people to understand.
看看萨米•杰克斯吧  杰克斯太太实在受不了
Look at Sammy Jankis. His own wife couldn't deal with it.
怎么都不能让他恢复记忆
I told you about how she tried to get him to snap out of it.
她终于来办公室见我
Eventually she came to see me at the office. I found out all kinds of shit.
说用尽办法强逼萨米记忆
She told me about life with Sammy, how she treated him.
谢谢你见我
Thank you for seeing me.
甚至要萨米把食物收藏起来
It got to the point where she'd get Sammy to hide food all around the house.
要他记着收藏地点
Then she'd stop feeding him to see if his hunger...
否则就挨饿
would make him remember where he'd hidden the food.
她不是狠心  只是希望萨米康复
She wasn't a cruel person. She just wanted old Sammy back.
你认为萨米在假装
Mr. Shelby, you know all about Sammy and you've decided that he's faking.
公司并没有说萨米假装
Mrs. Jankis, the company's position isn't that Sammy is faking anything...
只是认为他的病不是…
just that his condition can't be shown to be...
我只想知道你的真正看法
I just want to know what your honest opinion about Sammy is.
案件在上诉  我们不应该讨论
We shouldn't even be talking like this while the case is still open to appeal.
- 我不会提出上诉  - 那么你想怎么样？
- I'm not appealing the decision.      - Then why are you here?
当我看到萨米
Try to understand. When I look at Sammy...
我看的不是植物人
I don't see some... vegetable.
而是以前的萨米
I see my same old Sammy.
我总是抱有希望  总希望他完全是心理作祟
What do you think that's like for me to suspect he might be imagining this whole problem...
总希望有办法…
and that if I just could say the right thing...
让他痊愈
he'd snap out of it and go back to being normal?
如果萨米确实无药可救
If I knew that my old Sammy were truly gone...
那么我会抛开过去  爱现在的萨米
then I could say good-bye and start loving this new Sammy.
一天抱有希望  一天就死心不息
As long as I have doubt, I can't say good-bye and move on.
你要我怎么样？
What do you want from me?
我要你撇开公事半分钟
I want you to forget the company you work for for 30 seconds...
告诉我萨米是不是假装
and tell me if you really believe that Sammy's faking his condition.
我需要知道…你真正的想法
I need to know... what you honestly believe.
我相信萨米有记忆能力
I believe that Sammy should be physically capable of making new memories.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我以为帮了她  以为她只是要一个答案
I thought I helped her. I thought she just needed some kind of answer.
以为什么答案都不重要
I didn't think it was important what the answer was...
以为她只要一个可信的答案
just that she had one to believe.
- 这么好的车  你应该上锁  - 你是谁？
- A car this nice you should lock.      - Who the fuck are you?
- 你的朋友泰迪   - 证明一下
- Teddy, your buddy.      - Prove it.
你告诉过我萨米的事
Sammy. Remember Sammy? You told me about Sammy!
天啊
Geez!
你在我车里干什么？
What the fuck are you doing in my car?
你连幽默感也没有了？
What, your sense of humor went with the memory?
- 你为什么在这里  知道吗？ - 有未了结的事
- Do you even know why you're here?      - Unfinished business.
莱尼  告诉你吧
Lenny, let me inform you.
你的事已经了结
Your business here is very much finished.
- 你为了娜塔莉娅  所以还在这里  - 谁是娜塔莉娅？
- You're still here because of Natalie.      - Who's Natalie?
傻瓜  你刚从谁的家走出来？
Schmuck, whose house do you think you just walked out of?
对  看看照片吧  你肯定有她的照片
That's right. Take a look at your pictures. I bet you got one of her.
拍得好啊  大摄影师
Nice shot, Leibovitz.
记下来吧  不要相信她
You'll wanna make a note. You can't trust her.
为什么？
Yeah? Why's that?
因为她看出你有钱…
Because by now she's taken a look at this suit and the car...
打算利用你  捞点油水
and she's starting to figure out ways of turning the situation to her advantage.
她已经把你搭上手了
She's already got you staying with her, for Christ's sakes.
你不可以回她的家  我介绍你入住间旅馆吧
You can't go back in there. Let me give you the name of a motel.
- 碰到我  算你运气好  - 那女的为什么碰不得？
- You're lucky I ran into you. That broad's bad news.      - What do you mean, "bad news"?
她涉及毒品
She's involved with drugs.
看到了吗？
Look. These. You see these?
这是她工作的酒吧
This is the bar where she works.
她的男朋友是毒贩
Her boyfriend's a drug dealer.
她替他办事  传递消息
She takes orders for him, arranges meets.
他把讯息写在纸的背后
He writes messages on the back of these.
她趁斟酒时给他  偷偷替他传递
Then she slips him the answers when she serves him his drinks.
- 关我什么事？ - 因为她惹上了麻烦…
- Why should I care?      - Because when she gets jammed up...
打算利用你来替她解决
she's gonna use you to protect herself.
谁想找她的麻烦？
From who?
想知道她男朋友下落的人
Guys are gonna wanna know what happened to her boyfriend.
那人要找她出气  总有人受罪
Guys are gonna come after her. Somebody's gotta pay, Lenny.
一定有人受罪  也许她想用你来挡灾
Somebody always pays. Maybe she'll make it you.
是吗？也许她想利用你来挡灾  是不是？
Oh, yeah? Maybe she'll make it you. Is that it?
你担心她利用我来对付你
You worried that she's gonna use me against you?
- 不会  - 为什么不会？
- No.      - Why not?
因为她不认识我
Because she doesn't know who I am.
- 你为什么跟着我？ - 也许我想帮你
- Why are you following me?      - Maybe I wanna help.
她完全不知道你在调查什么  天才
She doesn't know anything about your investigation, okay, Einstein?
记下来吧
So write this down.
她提议帮你  其实是为了自已
When she offers to help, it'll be for her own reasons.
我没有骗你  用我这支笔记下来
I'm not lying. Take my pen. Write this down.
"不要相信她"
"Do not trust her."
- 现在高兴了没有？ - 你离开本地我才高兴
- There. You happy now?      - I won't be happy until you leave town.
为什么？
Why not?
你留下来  迟早有人会问
You ever wonder how long you can hang around here before people start asking questions?
问什么？
What sort of questions?
问你自己应该问的问题
The same sort of questions you should be asking yourself.
- 例如呢？ - 你为什么穿着名牌西服？开着名牌车？
- Like what?      - Like, how did you get this suit, the car?
- 我有钱    - 从哪里来的？
- I have money.      - From what?
我太太去世了  我以前在保险公司工作  买足了保险
My wife's death. I used to work in insurance. We were well covered.
你痛失娇妻  于是去买美州豹？
So in your griefyou wandered into a Jaguar dealership.
回答不出来吧
You don't have a clue, do you?
- 你连自已是谁都不知道    - 我知道
- You don't even know who you are.      - Yes, I do.
我没有失忆  意外前的事我统统记得
I don't have amnesia. I remember everything right up until the incident.
我叫莱纳•谢尔比  旧金山人
I am Leonard Shelby. I am from San Francisco...
那是以前的身份  你不知道现在的身份
That's who you were. You do not know who you are...
意外发生后…你变成怎么样的人
what you've become since... the incident.
你到处扮侦探
You wander around playing detective.
连扮了多久都不知道
You don't even know how long ago it was.
让我问问你  你推销保险  够钱穿名牌西装
Let me put it this way. Were you wearing designer suits when you sold insurance?
- 不是推销  是调查    - 对  你是调查员
- I didn't sell insurance. I investigated it.      - Right. You're an investigator.
- 你预先应该调查自已  - 谢谢你的忠告
- Maybe you should start investigating yourself.      - Thank you for the advice.
帮个忙  不要回到她家去
Look, do me a favor. Don't go back in there.
住旅馆好不好？
Will you take the motel out of town?
拜拜  莱尼
It's been fun, Lenny.
不要相信她
"Do not trust her."
"泰迪" "5550134"
"不要受他的骗"
"Don't believe his lies."
"特惠旅馆"
算了  我自己租房住
Fuck it. I need my own place.
"特惠旅馆"
杰克斯太太不应该逼我回答那种问题
No. She shouldn't have given me that responsibility.
我是保险调查员  不是医生
I'm a claims investigator, not a doctor.
对
Yeah. I guess.
我有很多顾虑
But I've got all sorts of other considerations.
法律责任  大笔的赔款…
Legal responsibility, large financial...
"绝不要接听电话"
哪位？
Who is this?
记下来  记下所发生的事情  记下来
Write this down. Write down what happened. Write it down.
集中精神  记着  找支笔
Concentrate. Keep it in mind. Find a pen.
发生了什么事？
What happened?
还用问？他打我
What does it look like? He beat the shit out of me.
谁？
Who?
达德啊！达德打我
Fuck, Leonard. Dodd. Dodd beat the shit out of me.
- 为什么？ - 为什么？都是因为你
- Why?      - Why? Because of you.
我照你的吩咐  去找他
Because I did what you told me to do! Go in and reason with him!
- 告诉他泰迪的事  结果挨打  - 冷静点
- Tell him about Teddy! Great fucking idea!      - Calm down. Take it easy.
不要怕
You're safe. It's okay.
坐下来
Come on. Just sit down.
坐
Sit down.
Here. Sit down.
不要怕
Okay. You're okay.
我拿些冰来给你敷脸
I'll just get some ice for your face.
拿着
Here.
我按照你的吩咐去做
I did exactly what you told me to do.
我去找达德
I went to Dodd...
告诉他杰米的钱、毒品…
and I told him that I didn't have any of Jimmy's money...
都不在我身上
or the drugs...
肯定统统被那个泰迪拿走了
and that this Teddy must have taken everything.
他怎么说的？
And what did he say?
他不相信我
He didn't believe me.
限我明天交出毒品  否则就杀我
He said if I don't have the drugs by tomorrow, he's gonna kill me.
说完了就打我
Then he just started hitting me.
他在哪里？
Where is he?
- 为什么问？ - 我要去见他
- Why?      - I'll go see him.
然后呢？
And?
打他  叫他去找泰迪
I'll give him some bruises of his own and tell him to look for a guy called Teddy.
他会杀了你的  莱尼
He'll kill you, Lenny.
我太太叫我莱尼
My wife used to call me Lenny.
是吗？
Yeah?
我讨厌莱尼这个名字
Yeah. I hated it.
达德这个人惹不得
This guy is so dangerous.
- 我们另想办法吧  - 不不
- Let's just think of something else, okay?      - No, no.
你告诉我他的模样 还有哪里能找到他就行了
You just tell me what he looks like... and where I can find him.
- 你有笔吧？ - 在手袋里
- Have you got a pen?      - In my purse.
他也许会找你
He'll probably find you.
- 什么意思？ - 我告诉他你的车
- What do you mean?      - I told him about your car.
为什么？
Why?
我挨不住打  只好说点东西
He was beating the shit out of me. I had to tell him something.
写下来吧
Just write it all down.
小心
Be careful.
不用担心
I'll be fine.
- 这么名贵的车  你应该上锁  - 你是谁？
- A car this nice you should lock.      - Who the fuck are you?
"绝不要接听电话"
柜台吗？
Front desk?
我是21号房的莱纳
Burt. Right. This is Mr. Shelby in room 21.
对  我不要接听电话
Yeah, that's the thing. I don't want any calls.
对  什么电话都不听
Nope. None at all.
- 什么事？ - 有人来过
- What's wrong?      - Somebody's come already.
- 是谁？ - 他自称达德
- Who?      - He calls himself Dodd.
他想要什么？
What does he want?
追问杰米和他的钱的下落  他以为我私吞了
He wants to know what happened to Jimmy and his money. He thinks I took it.
你有没有？
Did you?
没有
No.
- 怎么回事？ - 妈的
- What's this all about?      - Fuck!
你什么都不知道  你无知得相当舒服
You don't have a fucking clue, do you? You're just blissfully ignorant, aren't ya?
- 我有种病  - 我知道你的病
- I have this condition.      - I know all about your fucking condition, Leonard!
我可能比你更清楚  你什么都不知道
Probably know more about it than you do. You don't have a fucking clue about anything else.
什么事？
What happened?
杰米去见了一个叫泰迪的人
What happened is that Jimmy went to meet some guy named Teddy.
他拿了很多钱去  却一去不返
He took a lot of money with him, and he never came back.
杰米的拍档以为我是合谋  我连你认不认识泰迪都不知道
Jimmy's partners think I set him up. I don't know if you know this Teddy, or how well.
- 我也不知道    - 不要维护他
- Neither do I.      - Don't protect him!
- 我没有维护他  - 帮帮我
- I'm not.      - Help me.
怎么帮？
How?
替我铲除达德
Get rid of Dodd for me.
- 什么？ - 杀掉他  我付你钱
- What?      - Kill him. I'll pay you.
什么？我不会为钱杀人
What do you think I am? I'm not gonna kill someone for money.
如果为爱呢？
What then? Love?
那么会为什么？
What would you kill for?
- 你肯为太太杀人   - 那是另一回事
- You'd kill for your wife, wouldn't you?      - That's different.
- 对我是同一回事   - 不要谈我太太
- Not to me. I wasn't fucking married to her.      - Hey, don't talk about my wife.
我要谈谁  就谈谁
I can talk about whoever the fuck I want!
无论我说什么  你都记不得
I can say whatever I want and you won't remember.
骂你老婆是婊子  我们还可以做朋友
I could call your wife a fucking whore and we could still be friends.
- 冷静点   - 你根本不知道害怕
- Calm down.      - Easy for you to say. You can't get scared.
- 你个白痴   - 不要冲动  这事跟我无关
- You don't know how, you fucking idiot!      - Take it easy. This has nothing to do with me.
可能有关！你怎么知道无关？
Maybe it does. How the fuck would you know? You don't know a fucking thing!
- 你不怕死  不过会生气？ - 会
- You can't get scared, but can you get angry?      - Yes.
你这个该死的猪
You pathetic piece of shit.
无论我说什么…
I can say whatever the fuck I want...
你都莫名其妙  死蠢材
and you won't have a fucking clue, you fucking retard!
- 住口    - 知不知道？我会利用你
- Shut your mouth.      - You know what? I'm gonna use you.
我声明会利用你
I'm telling you now, because I'm gonna enjoy it so much more...
你个神经病照样会给我利用
if I know that you could stop me if you weren't such a fucking freak.
你丢掉了笔？
Did you lose your pen?
太倒霉了  神经病  否则你会记下…
That's too bad, freak. Otherwise, you could write yourself a little note...
娜塔莉娅恨透你了  同时认为你老婆是个婊子
about how much Natalie hates your retarded guts and that I called your wife a fuckin' whore.
- 不要再说了   - 不准再说你老婆是婊子？
- Don't say another fuckin' word.      - About your whore of a wife?
据说短期失忆这种病
I read about your condition, Leonard.
其中一个成因… 是性病
You know what one of the causes of short-term memory loss is? Venereal disease.
也许你的淫贱老婆搞过有性病的男人
Maybe your cunt of a fucking wife sucked one too many diseased cocks...
把你传染成了白痴
and turned you into a fucking retard!
死神经病
You sad, sad freak.
我想说什么就说什么
I can say whatever the fuck I want...
你不会记得
and you won't remember.
我们依然做好朋友
We'll still be best friends...
甚至做情人
or maybe even lovers.
妈的
Fuck.
再见
I'll see you soon.
集中精神  找支笔记下来
Stay focused. Find a pen.
记下来  记下来
Gotta write this down. Gotta write it down.
集中精神…
Concentrate. Concentrate. Concentrate.
记住  记住…
Keep it in mind. Keep it in mind. Keep it in mind.
找支笔  我要找支笔
Come on. Gotta find a pen. I gotta find a pen.
记下来  统统记下来
Write this down. Write this down, exactly what happened.
记下所发生的事情
Gonna write down exactly what happened. Come on.
快点！我要找支笔！
I gotta find a pen. Geez! Come on.
集中精神
Keep focused. Keep focused.
记住  快找支笔
Keep it in mind. Come on. Find a pen.
记下来  记下所发生的事情
Write this note. Write down what happened.
集中精神  记下来
Write it down. Concentrate. Keep it in mind.
发生了什么事？
What happened?
还用问？他打我
What does it look like? He beat the shit out of me.
谁？
Who?
达德啊！达德打我
Fuck, Leonard. Dodd. Dodd beat the shit out of me.
喂
Hello?
我是柜台的波特
It's Burt, from the front desk.
- 什么事？  - 你吩咐过不接电话
- Yeah?      - I know you said you didn't want any calls.
可是这个人自称警察
But this guy called. He's on the phone now. He says he's a cop.
- 警察？ - 是的
- A cop?      - Yeah.
他说…他有你要的资料
He says you're really gonna wanna know what he has to say.
我不喜欢讲电话  我要面对面谈
I'm not too good on the phone. I need to look people in the eye when I talk to them.
去沙发歇歇吧  会很舒服的
You can crash on the couch. It's comfortable.
坐吧
Just have a seat.
谢谢
Thanks.
你认为需要多久？
How long do you think it's gonna take you?
多久才找得到杀妻仇人？
You told me you were looking for the guy who killed your wife?
要看他是在本地还是在外地
That depends on if he's here in town or if he's moved on.
我有他的资料
I have my file here.
让我问问你  你既然资料齐全…
Can I ask you something? If you have all of that information...
为什么警方不替你缉凶？
then why haven't the police found him for you?
- 警方不肯缉凶    - 为什么？
- They're not looking for him.      - Why not?
他们认为已经没有凶手  我把经过告诉了他们
They don't think he exists. You see, I told them what I remembered.
我正在睡觉
I was asleep.
突然醒来
Something woke me up.
她的床是凉的  她已下床很久了
Her side ofthe bed was cold. She'd obviously been out of bed for a while.
肯定有第二个凶手
There had to be a second man.
他从后面袭击我
Somebody hit me from behind. I remember.
此后  我什么都不记得了
It's about the last thing that I do remember.
警方不相信有第二个凶手
Look. The police did not believe me. If we check the police...
警方怎么解释案情？怎么解释枪和其他？
How did they explain what you do remember? The gun and stuff.
约翰•G很狡猾
John G. was clever.
很狡猾
He was clever.
他拿掉死者的枪  换上袭击过我的棍子
See, he took the dead man's gun, he replaced it with the sap that he hit me with.
留下我的枪和贼车  于是误导了警方
He left my gun and he left the get away car. He gave the police a complete package.
警方在死者手中的棍子上发现了我的血迹
They found the sap with my blood on it in the dead man's hand.
并且只找到我的枪
And they only found my gun.
于是断定只有一个凶手
They didn't need to look for anybody else.
我认为有第二个  可是我伤了脑子
I was the only guy who disagreed with the facts, and I had brain damage.
警方不会相信有脑病的人
The cops are not gonna believe someone in my condition.
如果需要  你可以在这里住几天
Leonard, you can stay here for a couple of days if it'll help you.
谢谢
Thanks.
我要上班去了
I have to go back to work.
不用客气
So, just make yourself at home.
随便看电视  随便吃东西
You can watch TV oryou can have some food, whatever you want, okay?
- 不用客气   - 一件事
- Make yourself at home.      - One thing.
- 我想记得你   - 我叫娜塔莉娅
- Something to remember you by.      - My name is Natalie.
娜塔莉娅
"Natalie."
"记住萨米•杰克斯"
- 什么事？  - 有人来过
- What's wrong?      - Somebody's come already.
"接我电话"
- 免费   - 谢谢
- On the house.      - Thanks.
你确实有问题
You really do have a problem.
正如警察所说的一样
Just like that cop said.
你有病
Your condition.
没有人十全十美
Nobody's perfect.
你最后记得的是什么？
What's the last thing that you do remember?
- 我太太  - 真是多情
- My wife.      - That's sweet.
垂死…
Dying.
我太太垂死的情形
I remember my wife dying.
我替你换一杯
Let me get you another one.
这个杯子有灰尘
I think this one's dusty.
你为什么找我？想要什么？
Why are you calling me? What do you want?
我知道你是警察   我犯了法？
I know you're a cop, but what do you want? Have I done something wrong?
还是做了坏事？
I don't know. Something bad, maybe.
为什么问我？我记不得了  你反正不会相信
Why are you asking me? I can't remember what I've done. You wouldn't believe me anyway.
你不会相信我有这种病
Because of my condition. You don't believe someone with this condition.
就像我不相信萨米一样！
Nobody believed Sammy! I didn't even fucking believe Sammy!
"费迪斯酒吧"
"Ferdy's Bar."
"下班来  娜塔莉娅"
"Come by after. Natalie."
啤酒  麻烦你
I'll have a beer, please.
- 要什么？ - 啤酒  麻烦你
- What do you want?      - A beer, please.
你穿成那模样来喝啤酒？
You can't just waltz in here dressed like that and ask for a beer.
- 你们有服装规定？ - 你为什么来这儿？
- What, is there a dress code?      - Why are you here?
- 我想找个叫娜塔莉娅的人  - 我就是
- I'm meeting someone called Natalie.      - That's me.
我们见过面  是不是？
Yeah. We met before, right?
- 那么我来做什么？ - 不知道  你自己说好了
- Then why am I here?      - I don't know. Why don't you tell me.
我记不得  我没有短期记忆
I don't remember. I have no short-term memory. It's not amnesia.
- 原来你是那个失忆的人  - 你怎么知道？
- You're the memory guy.      - How do you know about me?
我男朋友提过你
My boyfriend told me about you.
- 你男朋友叫什么？ - 杰米•格兰斯  认识吗？
- Yeah? Who's your boyfriend?      - Jimmy Grants. Do you know him?
不认识
No.
他认识你  提到过你
He knows you. He told me about you.
说你住在特惠旅馆
He said you were staying at the Discount.
前不久有警察来找过你
In fact, a cop came by earlier, was looking for you.
说要找一个…
Said he was looking for a guy who can't remember anything...
懵懵懂懂的人
wouldn't know how he got here or what he'd done.
说我这里很多这种人
Said I get a lot of guys around here like that.
酗酒是短期失忆的一个原因
Chronic alcoholism is one cause of short-term memory loss.
- 你叫泰迪？ - 不是  我叫莱纳
- Are you Teddy?      - No. My name's Leonard.
- 泰迪派你来的？ - 我不知道
- Did Teddy send you?      - I don't know.
- 杰米现在怎样了？ - 我也不知道
- What's happened to Jimmy?      - I don't know that either.
- 对不起  - 你什么都不记得了？
- Sorry.      - You don't remember anything?
记不得去过哪里 做过什么
You don't remember where you've been or what you've just done.
记不得  我没有短期记忆  什么都忘掉了
No. I can't make new memories. Everything just fades.
- 那么你来做什么？ - 我在口袋里找到这个
- Then why did you come here?      - I found this in my pocket.
你的口袋？
Your pocket.
酒吧赌注  有兴趣参加吗？
Bar bet. Care to contribute?
- 不用客气   - 彩金好多
- No, thanks.      - It's for a lot of money.
参加嘛  是慈善的
Come on. Proceeds are going to charity. Help me out.
谢谢你
Thank you.
- 免费   - 谢谢
- On the house.      - Thanks.
谁也不相信我
It's completely fucked because nobody believes you.
脑部受损  连说话也没有人信
It's amazing what a little brain damage will do for your credibility.
我以前不信萨米  应该有此报应
I guess it's some kind of poetic justice for not believing Sammy.
患我这种病的人…
You know the truth about my condition, Officer?
什么都不知道
You don't know anything.
生气生得莫名其妙
You feel angry, you don't know why.
内疚得莫名其妙
You feel guilty, you have no idea why.
无论什么  十分钟就忘掉
You could do anything and not have the faintest idea 10 minutes later.
萨米的事…
Like Sammy. What if I've done something like Sammy?
我有没有告诉你萨米和他太太的事？
I didn't tell you what happened to Sammy and his wife?
她到我办公室见我  我以为她在试探
She came to see me at my office. I thought she was trying to catch me off guard...
我没有对她说真心话
so I didn't tell her what I really thought, but I never said that he was faking...
只说他的病是心理上的  而不是生理的
just that his condition was mental, not physical.
她回家  替萨米做最后的测试
I found out later that she went home and gave Sammy his final exam.
萨米  到时间替我打针了
Sammy? It's time for my shot.
她深信萨米爱她
She knew beyond a doubt that he loved her.
于是用这个测试办法
So she found a way to test him.
萨米  到时间替我打针了
Sammy. It's time for my shot.
她以为可以拆穿他
She really thought she'd call his bluff.
打了
There you go.
否则  她不想再活下去
Or she just didn't wanna live with the things she'd put him through.
萨米
Sammy.
到时间替我打针了
It's time for my shot.
不会痛
It won't hurt.
她不省人事  接着就死了
She went into a coma and never recovered.
萨米不明白  也不能解释
Sammy couldn't understand or explain what happened.
从此长住疗养院
He's been in a home ever since.
连妻子去世也不知道
He doesn't even know that his wife is dead.
我看错了萨米  看错了他太太
I was wrong about Sammy, and I was wrong about his wife.
她不是为钱
She wasn't interested in the money.
只是想了解病情
She just needed to understand his problem.
他对惯性没有反应  可是他不是骗子
His brain didn't respond to conditioning. But he wasn't a con man.
她以为萨米没有变
When she looked into his eyes, she thought he could be the same person.
我也以为萨米认得我
When I looked into his eyes, I thought I saw recognition.
我现在知道是假装的
Now I know. You fake it.
他假装认得人
If you think you're supposed to recognize somebody, you just pretend to.
也许是为了博取赞许
You bluff it to get a pat on the head from the doctors.
也许是为了冒充正常
You bluff it to seem less of a freak.
什么毒贩？
What drug dealer?
"事实6：车牌 SG1371U"
"纹身店"
"事实6：车牌…"
- 莱尼  你好  - 这是私人地方
- Hey, Lenny, how you doing?      - It's private back here.
- 我们是认识的   - 你怎么知道我在这里？
- It's okay. We know each other. Right, kid?      - How did you know I was in here?
你把美洲豹停在前面
The Jag's out front. Should have put it around back.
你还在这里做什么？北方有很多纹身店
What are you still doing here, Lenny? There's plenty of tattoo parlors up north.
我想趁还没忘记  纹下来
I guess I wanted to get something down before it slipped my mind.
- 把车匙给我吧  我帮你开走   - 不要紧
- Give me the keys. I'll move it.      - It'll be all right for a minute.
出去等吧
Wait out there.
给我一分钟  我有事告诉你
Give me a minute. I gotta get something for you.
"事实6：车牌 SG1371U"
Fact six: Car license SG137IU.
等一等  好不好？
Look. Wait a minute, will ya?
- 我要送你离开本地  - 为什么？
- We gotta get you out of here.      - Why?
多此一问  你要我说多少遍？
Man. Come on, Leonard. How many times I gotta tell you?
- 你在这里已经不安全了   - 为什么？
- It's not safe for you to hang around here anymore.      - Why not?
警察在找你
Because that cop's looking for you.
我要给你弄个新身份  新衣服
I gotta get you a new identity, some new clothes.
暂时换辆汽车  穿上去
A different car would do for now. So put these on.
什么警察？
What cop?
一个坏警察  他介绍你住特惠旅馆
He's a bad cop. He's the one that checked you into the Discount Inn.
他已经找你好几天了  蒙骗你  把信封塞进你门底下
He's been calling you for days, telling you shit, slipping envelopes under your door. Shit like that.
- 你怎知道？  - 他告诉我  以为好笑
- How do you know this?      - He told me. He thinks it's funny.
- 他在玩你   - 你胡说
- He's been laughing at you.      - You're full of shit.
不是  他知道你不爱讲电话…
I'm not. He knows you're no good on the phone, so he's been calling you.
所以找上门
Sometimes you don't answer the phone...
把信封塞进你门里  吓到你听电话
so he slips shit under your door to scare you into answering the phone again...
骗你说约翰•G是毒贩
giving you a line of crap about John G. Being some local drug dealer.
- 杰米•格兰斯  - 谁是杰米•格兰斯？
- Jimmy Grants.      - Who's Jimmy Grants?
杰米是毒贩
Leonard, Jimmy's the drug dealer.
警察在调查他
The cop wants to know how his operation's run.
无论如何  你牵涉进去了
He's got some score in mind. Somehow you're involved.
你怎么认识他的？
Uh-huh. How do you know him?
我是线人  他是外地警察  于是走在一起
I'm a snitch. He's a cop from out oftown. The local boys put us together.
假如他知道我帮你  一定会宰了我
If he knew I was helping you, he'd fucking kill me.
换上这些衣服吧  然后快点离开本地
So take these clothes, put them on and get the fuck out of here.
莱纳  快走吧
Come on, Leonard. Just go.
"泰迪" "5550134"
"不要受他骗"
你胡说
You are full of shit.
"下班后来找娜塔莉娅"
"Come by after. Natalie."
"费迪斯酒吧"
"Ferdy's Bar."
杰米
Hey, Jimmy.
对不起  我认错了人
I'm sorry. I thought you were somebody else.
对不起
Sorry.
不要紧
That's okay.
"下班后来找娜塔莉娅"
杰米•格兰斯在女友的酒吧贩毒？
So this Jimmy Grants deals drugs out ofthe bar where his girlfriend works?
他不会带她来  他会自己来吧？
But he's not gonna bring her along. He'll come by himself, right?
最好以贩毒罪名指控他
I always figured the drugs angle would be the best way to get him.
探长  我随时都准备好
No, Officer. I'm as ready as I'll ever be.
你来到了旅馆正门？你是什么样子？
You're in the lobby? What do you look like?
我马上出去
I'll be right there.
莱尼
Lenny.
你是盖玛探长？
Officer Gammell.
对  来吧
Yeah. Come on.
- 笑一笑   - 不要在这里
- Smile.      - Not here.
这里拍吧
Over here.
- 是探长还是盖玛探员？  - 知道吗？
- Is it Officer or Lieutenant Gammell?      - You know what?
不要写姓盖玛  写泰迪好了
Don't write Gammell, just Teddy.
- 为什么？ - 我正在做卧底
- Why?      - I'm undercover.
他会经过
This is the directions where he's going.
- 我的电话在下面   - 你不来？
- My number's on the bottom if you need me.      - You're not coming?
不来  不方便去
No. It wouldn't be appropriate.
拍得不错  拍得我瘦了些
Nice picture. I look thin.
莱尼
Hey, Lenny.
好好修理他
Make him beg.
泰迪
Teddy!
Hey, Teddy!
杰米
Jimmy.
- 你在这里做什么？ - 你是杰米•格兰斯？
- What the fuck are you doing here?      - You Jimmy Grants?
还有另一个杰米吗？白痴
Expecting any other Jimmys out here, Memory Man?
- 你记得我？ - 我记得你
- Do you remember me?      - Yeah, I remember you.
泰迪在哪里？
Where the fuck's Teddy?
怎么样？
Well?
贱种…你想怎么样？
Motherfuck... Fuckin' retard!
- 脱掉   - 你搞错了  大错特错
- Strip.      - You're making a big fucking mistake, pal.
脱掉
Strip!
我的拍档不是善男信女
My associates are not the kind of people you wanna piss off.
住口
Don't say anything else.
- 早知到那贱种不可靠   - 脱掉
- I knew I couldn't trust that fuck!      - Take it off.
贱人
Cocksucker.
裤子也脱掉
Your pants too.
- 为什么？ - 我不想沾血
- Why?      - I don't wanna get blood on them.
等一等  他有没有说我带了什么来？
Wait. Did he tell you what I was bringing?
- 脱裤子呀   - 我带了20万来！在车里！
- Take your fuckin' pants off!      - I've got 200 grand stashed in the car!
- 拿走吧！  - 你想讨价还价？
- Just take it!      - You think you can bargain with me?
- 把钱拿走吧！    - 我不要你的臭钱！
- Take the money and walk away!      - I don't want your fuckin' money.
那你要什么？
Then what?
- 你要什么？  - 我想要回我的生活
- What do you want from me?      - I want my fuckin' life back!
"萨米"
Sammy.
他说萨米  他认识萨米？
He said "Sammy". How does he know about Sammy?
糟糕
Oh, fuck.
我做了什么？
What have I done?
先生  帮帮忙  有人受了重伤
Mister, I need help. There's a guy in here, he's hurt bad.
- 需要看医生   - 好
- We gotta get him to a doctor.      - All right.
我不知道发生了什么  我有失忆症
I don't know what happened. I've got this memory thing.
- 我认识你吗？ - 不认识  我是警察
- Do I know you?      - No. Don't worry. I'm a cop.
- 他还有气吗？ - 不知道  也许有
- Is he still breathing?      - I don't know. Maybe.
你们在这里干什么？
What the hell were you guys doing down here?
我不记得  我有病
I don't remember. I have this condition.
他比你惨  他死了
I hope it's not as serious as his, 'cause this guy's dead.
哎唷  莱尼  痛死我了
Ow! Lenny! That shit kills!
你现在记得我了？你是个警察
So you remember me now, huh? You are a fuckin' cop.
是我帮你找到他
Yeah. And I'm the guy that helped you find him.
起来  起来
Get up. Get up.
莱尼  你误会了
Lenny, you got the wrong idea.
他是谁？他认识我
Who is that? He knew me.
当然  他强奸你老婆  打伤你
Of course he did. He raped your wife. He fucked up your brain.
胡说！他不是凶手
Bullshit. He's not the guy.
他叫杰米•格兰斯  又名约翰•G  查查你的纹身吧
His name is James F. Grants. John G. Check your tattoos.
- 为什么他带20万来？ - 什么？
- What was he bringing the 200 grand for?      - What?
- 用来干什么？ - 我告诉他我有大批安非他命
- What was it for?      - A load of amphetamines I told him I had.
- 你们买卖毒品？ - 是  还有你的事
- Is this a drug deal?      - No. Yeah, that and your thing.
杰米是你的仇家  我只是乘机捞油水
Look, Leonard, Jimmy's your guy. I just figured we'd make a few dollars on the side.
- 他怎么认识我的？ - 特惠旅馆
- How did he know me?      - The Discount Inn. He dealt out of there.
旅馆的人是他朋友
The guy at the front desk let him know if anybody came snooping around.
一看你拍照  就通知杰米
He called Jimmy the minute he saw you taking a picture ofthe dump.
- 你在利用我  - 不  你分得一半的钱
- You're fucking using me.      - No! You get half!
他认识萨米！怎么会认识萨米？
He knew about Sammy! Why would I tell him about fuckin' Sammy?
你见人就说萨米的事
You tell everybody about Sammy, everybody who'll listen.
"记得萨米•杰克斯吗？"
"Remember Sammy Jankis?" "Remember Sammy Jankis?"
你愈说愈精彩
Great story. Gets better every time you tell it.
这也没什么错  我们都这么做
So you lie to yourself to be happy.
你在自己骗自已
There's nothing wrong with that. We all do it.
你只记得你想记得的事
Who cares if there's a few little details you'd rather not remember?
- 你说什么？ - 不知道
- What the fuck are you talking about?      - I don't know.
你太太事后还活着
Your wife surviving the assault.
她不相信你有病
Her not believing your condition.
她内心痛苦无比
The torment and pain and anguish tearing her up inside.
胰岛素
The insulin.
那是萨米  不是我
That's Sammy, not me. I told you about Sammy.
对  你不断这样对自己说
Yeah, right. Like you tell yourselfover and over again.
用惯性法来帮自己记忆
Conditioning yourself to remember.
- 用重复又重复的方法来学习   - 萨米让太太自杀
- Learning through repetition.      - Sammy let his wife kill herself.
- 萨米进了医院   - 萨米是老千  是假装的
- Sammy ended up in an institution.      - Sammy was a con man, a faker.
我从没说萨米假装
I never said that Sammy was faking.
你暴露出他的真面目...他的骗局
You exposed him for what he was... a fraud.
不过  我是错的
But I was wrong. That's the whole point.
- 萨米的妻子来找我   - 萨米没有妻子
- See, Sammy's wife came to me.      - Sammy didn't have a wife.
你的妻子才有糖尿病
It was your wife who had diabetes.
疼
Ouch.
我太太没有糖尿病
My wife wasn't diabetic.
你肯定？
You sure?
- 不要！  - 她没有糖尿病
- Ouch. Cut it out.      - She wasn't diabetic.
我难道不清楚我太太？你有什么不妥？
You think I don't know my own wife? What the fuck is wrong with you?
你只记得你想记得的事
I guess I can only make you remember the things you wanna be true.
- 就像杰米一样    - 他不是我的仇人
- Like old Jimmy down there.      - He's not the right guy.
对你来说  他是
He was to you.
你报了仇  趁记得  好好开心吧
Come on. You got your revenge. Enjoy it while you still remember.
是不是真正的仇人  有什么关系？
What difference does it make whether he was your guy or not?
- 有很大的关系   - 你反正不会记得的
- It makes all the difference.      - Why? You're never gonna know.
- 我会的   - 你不会
- Yes, I will.      - No, you won't.
我会的  我总之会的
I will. Somehow I'll know.
- 你不会记得！   - 这次我会
- You won't remember!      - When it's done, I will know. It'll be different.
我本来以为你会  但你记不得
I thought so too. In fact, I was sure of it, but you didn't!
对  真正的约翰•G
That's right. The real John G.
一年多前我帮你找到他  他已经死了
I helped you find him over a year ago. He's already dead.
- 不要再骗我   - 莱尼
- Don't lie to me anymore.      - Look, Lenny.
你太太的档案是我给你的  我相信你
I was the cop assigned to your wife's case. I believed you.
认为你应该报仇
I thought you deserved a chance for revenge.
我帮你找到另外的凶手
I'm the one that helped you find the other guy in your bathroom that night...
那个打你的头  强奸你老婆的人
the guy that cracked your skull and fucked your wife.
我们找到他  你杀了他
We found him. You killed him.
可是你记不得  于是我帮你再去找
But you didn't remember. So I helped you start looking again...
找那个你已经杀掉的人
Looking for the guy you already killed.
是吗？那么他是谁？
Yeah? So who was he?
是谁有什么关系？
Just some guy. Does it even matter who?
没有原因  也没有阴谋  只是倒霉罢了
No reason, Lenny. No conspiracy. Just bad fucking luck.
两个吸毒的以为你太太独自在家  搞出了事
Couple of junkies too strung out to realize your wife didn't live alone.
你杀了他  我还以为你记得
But when you killed him, I was so convinced that you'd remember.
不过  你忘掉了
But it didn't stick.
什么都不记得  这次也不会记得
Like nothing ever sticks. Like this won't stick.
照片是我拍的  在你报仇的时候拍的
I took that picture... just when you did it.
看  你多开心
Look how happy you are.
我想你再开心点
I wanted to see that face again.
- 多谢啊  - 你这个混蛋
- Gee, thanks.      - Fuck you.
你有仇报  生活就有目的
I gave you a reason to live, and you were more than happy to help.
你记不得真相  你自已制造真相
You don't want the truth. You make up your own truth.
例如那警察档案
Like your police file.
谁撕掉里面的12页纸？
It was complete when I gave it to you. Who took out the 12 pages?
- 可能是你    - 不是我  是你
- You, probably.      - No, it wasn't me. See, it was you.
- 我为什么撕掉？ - 为了替自己制造一个解不开的谜
- Why would I do that?      - To create a puzzle you could never solve.
你知道有多少个镇吗？
You know how many towns?
有多少个约翰•G？
How many John G.'s or James G.'s?
我就是个约翰•G
Shit, Lenny. I'm a fucking John G.
- 你叫泰迪    - 我妈妈叫我泰迪
- Your name is Teddy.      - My mother calls me Teddy.
我的姓名是约翰•爱德华•盖玛
My name's John Edward Gammell.
振作起来吧
Cheer up.
你要找  不愁没有约翰•G
There's plenty of John G.'s for us to find.
你只知道发牢骚
All you do is moan.
只有我知道你做过什么
I'm the one that has to live with what you've done.
我在幕后指导
I'm the one that put it all together.
你只是在扮侦探  你活在梦中
You wander around, you're playing detective. You're living a dream, kid.
为亡妻怀念  有生活的目的
A dead wife to pine for. A sense of purpose to your life.
即使没有我  你也不会罢手
A romantic quest that you wouldn't end even if I wasn't in the picture.
- 我应该杀了你   - 收手吧  莱尼
- I should kill you.      - Quit it. Lenny, come on.
你不是杀手  所以你才那么在行
You're not a killer. That's why you're so good at it.
干什么？知道几点吗？
What are you doing? You know what time it is?
喝啤酒去吧  我请客
It's beer o'clock. I'm buying.
操
Fuck.
我不是杀手
I'm not a killer.
我只想补救错误
I'm just someone who wanted to make things right.
"泰迪" "5550134"
我应不应该忘记你的话？
Can I just let myself forget what you've told me?
"不要受他的骗"
应不应该忘记你让我做的事？
Can I just let myself forget what you made me do?
你以为我想再去解另一个谜？
You think I just want another puzzle to solve?
再去找另一个约翰•G？
Another John G. To look for?
你也是约翰•G
You're a John G.
你可以做我的约翰•G
So you can be my John G.
"事实6：车牌…"
"SG1371U"
我要自欺才能够快乐？
Do I lie to myself to be happy?
泰迪  对于你…
In your case, Teddy...
我会
Yes, I will.
那辆车不是你的
Hey, that's not your car!
- 现在是了   - 你怎么可以开走？
- It is now.      - Jesus Christ, you can't take it!
- 为什么不可以？ - 因为车主刚被你杀死
- Why not?      - Because the guy you just killed owns it!
有人会认得
Somebody'll recognize it!
被人误当成死人  比误当成杀手好
I think I'd rather be mistaken for a dead guy than a killer.
我会用一段时候
I might hang on to this for a while.
莱尼
Lenny.
帮我找车钥匙好吗？
Will you help me find the keys?
帮我找车钥匙
Help me find my keys.
我要相信世界不是我想象出来的
I have to believe in a world outside my own mind.
我要相信我所做的事仍然有意义
I have to believe that my actions still have meaning...
即使我记不得做了什么
even if I can't remember them.
我要相信  即使闭上眼睛…
I have to believe that when my eyes are closed...
世界仍然存在
the world's still here.
我相不相信世界仍然存在？
Do I believe the world's still here?
世界仍然存在？
Is it still out there?
没错
Yeah.
我们需要记忆去确定自己的身份
We all need mirrors to remind ourselves who we are.
我并不例外
I'm no different.
"纹身店"
"事实6：车牌 SG1371U"
我到了哪里？
Now, where was I?